Today, we're studying pendulums, which are
a
classic example of oscillations and
periodic
motions, and a pendulum is basically a bob
on
a string that goes back and forth, and to
do
pendulum problems, we would probably need
to
find the period, which is a really common
question.
And what you'll see later is that the cool
thing
about pendulum is that mass doesn't really
affect
the period at all. What is a pendulum?
A simple pendulum needed is having a bob,
which
is this small mass, let's call this a bob,
attached
to a string of length L.
So this would have a length of L. And it's
gonna
swing back and forth across a pivot.
Now, there are some key vocabulary you
will
need. There is a period, or t, which is
the
time it takes to complete one full
oscillation.
To complete one.
So it's basically the same thing as a
period
in trigonometry. The time, or the length
of
x that it takes to have one full, you
know,
rotation. And frequency is the number
of cycles per second. So if you think
about
it, frequency is the same, basically the
opposite
of period. Frequency is one over t.
Because period, we're measuring the time
off
of the number of oscillations. And
frequency,
we're measuring the number of oscillations
off
of time. Now, what are the forces on a
pendulum
ball? Well, when we map it out, we would
have
the force of gravity.
We have the tension force, f t.
And that's basically all we have. The
reason
why, in this case, the ball goes this way
is
because of a component in the tension
force,
the x component, that actually makes it
go.
And that is called the tangential
component.
So we call this tangential component.
And keep in mind that this is not a force,
it's
just a component of the tension force.
Now, there is a key formula that you will
have
to use. And this formula is t equals two
pi
root l over g.
And basically what this says is that the
period
is equal to two pi times the length over
the
acceleration of gravity. However, there is
one
key important thing to note, especially in
experimental
physics when you're actually doing the
lab,
and I'm sure your teachers will also
stress
this as well. This formula approximates
small
angle. So what that means is that this
formula only works when your angle is
relatively
small, when theta is relatively small.
If it's large, when your theta is large,
this
formula will probably not work. That's why
when
doing experiments, try to set the pendulum
off
at a relatively small arc.
Now, one other important thing to note is
that
mass doesn't affect the period.
As you can see in this formula, you don't
see
mass anywhere. The period only depends on
the
length of the string, and of course
gravity,
but that's really basically what planet
you're
on, and usually it's conducted on Earth.
So that means that it doesn't matter
whether
this ball is one gram, one kilogram, or
even
one ton at that matter, the period will
always
be the same as long as the length of the
string
is the same. And this formula is basically
all
you need to know for AP and IB in regards
to
pendulum motion, because you can calculate
everything
you need. If a multiple choice question,
let's
say, asks you what will happen to the
length
if the period doubles, well, you know that
the
length will increase by four, because the
length
is proportional to the square of the
period,
because it's square-rooted here. And if
the
question asks what if the mass has
doubled,
well, you know that the period doesn't
change.
So just base all your answers off of this
formula.
Let's say we have a question that asks us
to
solve the period. Let's say we have a
pendulum
of mass of one kilogram, and
the length of the string is 0.850 metres,
and
you have to find its period. Well, we just
plug
this in. T equals 2 pi root L over g.
We know L is 0.85 metres, and mass really
doesn't
matter, because you don't need mass.
g is 9.81, and you can
see that 0.85 over 9.81 would be 0.0866,
so the square root of that would be 0.294.
And the ultimate period would be 1.85
seconds,
because period is the time it takes for
one
pole oscillation. So that's basically it
for
periods, and it's applied in real world as
well.
In, for example, pendulum clocks, they use
the
period of their pendulum to time-keep, and
it
really depends on a stable period, so it
must
be very, very accurate. Seismometers, I
think that's how you spell it, are
basically
pendulum-like systems that are used to
detect
vibrations, like earthquakes.
And also, another real-world application
that
you guys probably know a lot of is
playground
swings. And basically, using
your newly formed formula, you can
basically
approximate, let's assume that you swing
on
small angles, the amount, the time it
takes
for you to do a swing really doesn't
depend
on how high you are. It takes more time
when
you're higher or lower, as long as it's a
small
angle, the time it takes for you to do one
swing
is approximately always the same.
That is, of course, you don't take into
account
air resistance, and you assume there's no
other
factors like wind or things, but that's a
really,
really cool thing to know. And that's
basically
it about pendulums. Just remember this
formula,
and remember that mass does not affect the
pendulum
at all. Also make sure that you don't draw
this
force over here. It's a component of the
tension
force that the bob is being exerted on.
Thank you for watching, and I hope you
learned
something from this video.